<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second part of Vox populi, or Gondomar appearing in the likenes of Matchiauell in a Spanish parliament wherein are discouered his treacherous &amp; subtile practises to the ruine as well of England, as the Netherlandes. Faithfully transtated [sic] out of the Spanish coppie by a well-willer to England and Holland.</title>
            <title>Vox populi. Part 2</title>
            <author>Scott, Thomas, 1580?-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B15717</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842892</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176797</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240888525</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 22103</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S107190</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99842892e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B15717)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176797)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 676:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second part of Vox populi, or Gondomar appearing in the likenes of Matchiauell in a Spanish parliament wherein are discouered his treacherous &amp; subtile practises to the ruine as well of England, as the Netherlandes. Faithfully transtated [sic] out of the Spanish coppie by a well-willer to England and Holland.</title>
                  <title>Vox populi. Part 2</title>
                  <author>Scott, Thomas, 1580?-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 60 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>A Janss [i.e. N. Okes and J. Dawson],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Goricom [Gorinchem, i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication initialed: T. S. of V. [i.e. Thomas Scott, B.D.].</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC because copy catalogued lacks imprint; actual place of publication and printers' names from STC; Dawson printed dedication.</note>
                  <note>Engraved title page has blank spaces to left and right of Gondomar's head; leaf D3v line 1 begins: "thinke". This typesetting of the text, with  title page altered, is reissued in STC 22103.7--STC.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 22104a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page cropped, affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Spain --  Foreign relations --  1516-1700 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176797:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176797:1"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCES, FREDERICK and ELIZABETH, by the Grace of God, <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queene of Bohemia,</hi> Princes <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latines</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>AS ALSO</hi> To the most Illustrious and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, <hi>Maurice,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> Count of <hi>Nassau,</hi> &amp;c.
<list>
                  <item>Most High</item>
                  <item>Most Illustrious</item>
                  <item>Princes,</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT I haue adventured in these vnfaithfull times, so full of suspition and danger, to passe (without leaue) your guardes, and to presse into your Presence, I most humbly craue pardon, having I confesse no other excuse
<pb facs="tcp:176797:2"/> not vnmindfull of a Matchiavillian and<note place="margin">Divide, et Impera.</note> old Maxime; But I trust Almighty God (as hee hath already begun) will open the eyes of all Christian Kinges and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in time not onely to prie into, but ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to oppose, these his immense and ambitious designes, which else in time may fall heauie vpon our children and posteritie, I end; humbly beseeching the King of Kings and Kingdomes, the Almighty Lord of Hoastes: Most High, Most Illustrious Princes, to protect the persons of your selues and children, with his grace to multiplie your Honors and Dignities, foure-fold to restore your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states, and after many yeares to crowne you in Heaven, with the Diademes of Glorie and endles happines.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Who is most devoted vnto your <hi>Highnesses,</hi> in all Loyall affection <hi>T. S.</hi> of <hi>Ʋ.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:176797:2"/>
            <head>THE SPANISHE PARLIAMENT.
<figure>
                  <p>Ingentibus exidit ausis.</p>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the Spanish Parliament</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the shouts and acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of all true hearted English, for the safe and single returne of the Prince of Great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> had made the roofe of Heauen to resound, and with the noyse hād shooke such a terror into the ill affected body of <hi>Spaine,</hi> that a cold, and benumming feare, ran through her
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176797:3"/> ioynts, her friends began to bethinke themselues, of a timely recomfort, to finde the meanes a fresh to rouse vp her spirits, (by this time halfe repenting her selfe of parting with so pretious a pawne, (the possession whereof she imagined, might haue tied vs to haue precisely kept day, (though it were likely to haue had prooued more fatall vnto her, then euer was the gold of <hi>Thousouse</hi> to <hi>Cepio's</hi> Souldiers) and as it falleth out among sicke persons, some of soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der iudgement then the rest, about her in particular and euery one in generall giuing their best opinions, vndertooke (so she would be ruled) to rid her off that fit and distempered perplexity.</p>
            <p>And for this purpose appoynting for a further consultation to be at <hi>Seuill</hi> in <hi>Audaluzia,</hi> whether al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready the King with most of the Nobility had reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themselues in regard (they sayd) the English who were in number about seauen-score, had not long before eaten vp all the prouision in <hi>Madrid,</hi> and within thirty miles about, there came as truest and old friends to her estate, the Arch-bishop of <hi>Toledo,</hi> the Dukes of <hi>Medina Coeli,</hi> of <hi>Braganza,</hi> of <hi>Ville Hermosa,</hi> of <hi>Hijaz, D.</hi> of <hi>Infantado, D.</hi> of <hi>Cea, D.</hi> of <hi>Sesa, D.</hi> of <hi>Veragua,</hi> Marques of <hi>Malagon; Count de Penna-fiore, Count de Monterry, Count de Sanstephano, &amp;c. Escalona,</hi> the Marques of <hi>Castello, Rodrigo</hi> the Admirant and Constable of <hi>Castile, Count Olivares, Count Gondomar, Pedro de Toledo, Gonzales de Cordua, Lewes de Velasco,</hi> with sundry o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of remarke and note, of the chiefest Nobility, whither being come, and hauing made choyce of a goodly and faire Pallace, anciently belonging vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176797:3"/> the D. of <hi>Beiar</hi> principall of the family of the <hi>Zanigas,</hi> in a faire great Chamber hung with rich Arras, ouer the leather guilded. <hi>Guara Mazilla's,</hi> after many an enterchange of complement, each as his precedence required tooke his place, like a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of wise Physitians to consult of the state of that body and Kingdome, how with medicines (as Physitians call them) to preuent her future danger, withall for the present to repayre the ruine of her reputation and credit with the world, (since now her plots and practises are smoaked, their gordian knots vntwisted euen by children: Lastly, how to gaine by strong hand, what all this while shee could not compasse by artes and policie.</p>
            <p>Being all set and silent, the Duke of <hi>Medina Coeli,</hi> stoode vp and spake as followeth.</p>
            <p>My Lords, it hath pleased his Catholique Maiesty the King our Mr. to giue way to this our meeting and Parlamentary assembly, to consult and aduise among our selues, what course is most fittest to be holden of vs, in these tempestuous times, for the weather being changed, and the bright beames of our hopes ouer-cast, we are from euery side to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect rage and stormes. You are not ignorant how there is now a Parliament holden in <hi>England,</hi> that bode vs no good, in <hi>Holland</hi> a dayly consultation with present preparation, In <hi>France</hi> a Councell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with an vnaminity of Kings and Peeres, for some great vndertaking: How nerely then concernes it vs of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to be vigilant, and to looke about vs: first, for the maintenance and aduancement of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176797:4"/> the Catholique Religion, and holy Church: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for the defence of his Maiesties Kingdomes and Territories: Thirdly, to heare the grieuances of the people groaning vnder the heauy burthen of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action and oppression, though the couetuosnesse of publique offices. Fourthly, for the supply of the Treasury which a late hath beene much exhausted, partly by preparation by Sea against our Common enemies, <hi>Turkes,</hi> and <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and partly by the extraordinary entertainment of <hi>Charles</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> the charge wherof amounted to 49. thousand Ducates. Fift, and lastly, for giuing the world sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and the taking away of those vile scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dales and imputations, which euen within these few dayes haue beene, and are hourely cast vpon vs, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, (as they giue it out) in dealing doubly and dishonorably with <hi>England,</hi> concerning the Treaty of the Match.</p>
            <p>He hauing ended, the D. of <hi>Braganza</hi> the next began thus.</p>
            <p>I am sorry that I liue to see the day, that the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Spaine</hi> which was wont to dazle the eye of <hi>Europe</hi> with the vnsufferable splendor of its bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, should now be ouer cast with the blacke cloud of disgrace, and the name of a Spaniarde so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted ouer the world, become branded with the infamous attributes and epithites of false, ambitious, proud, and cruell, and those Nations who were wont to adore vs for our faith, contemne, and scorne vs now for treachery and falshood. Certes loyalty and the Religious obseruance of our promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176797:4"/> and faith, was anciently held our prime vertue, insomuch that <hi>Fey de Spagna</hi> grew into a Prouerbe, like the gold of <hi>Ophir</hi> out valewing any other, that I speake no new thing, or vntruth, you may plainely perceiue it by the multitude of discourses, pamphlets and pasquills that are dayly vented against vs from all parts of the World, wherein wee are iested at, derided, disgraced, by verses and vnseemely Pictures, especially of late dayes, from <hi>Holland, France,</hi> and <hi>England:</hi> yea as I vnderstand in songs and Ballades, sung vp and downe the Streetes in many places: whence this imputation, vpon so iust and braue a Nation, so potent a Monarch (at the brandishing of whose sword <hi>Europe</hi> trembles) should proceede, I cannot ghesse, yet desire to be satisfied herein, in the King my Mr. and Kinsmans behalfe, my Kinsman, for you all know my neere alliance vnto his Maiesty, and my Poesie may intimate no lesse vnto the world which is <hi>Pues vos, nos,</hi> after you, we, being next in blood if the issue Royall should faile.</p>
            <p>But I am a fraide the ill carriage of some priuate men at home, (perhaps our Embassadors in For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine parts,) haue throwne this aspersion vpon vs, hauing eyther giuen abroad to many ouertures of our designes, or attempted their ends with ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much hast and violence, which in time and by gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hand might haue beene easier won, as a bough whose fruite we meane to gather, is brough downe by degrees, which else might breake and we loose our longing.</p>
            <p>Surely, in the first, me thinke our Nation should not easily offend, we beeing esteemed the most close
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176797:5"/> and reserued to our selues in the world, as the euent of our greatest and most important actions haue sufficiently shewne. Did we not in 88. carry our bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse for <hi>England</hi> so cunningly and secretly as well, in that well dislembled treaty with the English neere <hi>Ostend,</hi> whereto for vs were deputed, <hi>Aremberge, Champigny, Richardot</hi> and other, as in bringing our Nauy to their shores, while their Commanders and Captaines were at bowles vpon the hoe of <hi>Plimouth,</hi> and had my Lord <hi>Alonso Guzman,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina Sidonia</hi> had but the resolution (but in truth his Commission was otherwise) he might haue suprized them as they lay at Anker, and the like. In <hi>Ireland</hi> when <hi>Don Ivan d' Aquila</hi> had gotten footing in the Irish ground ere any of the mist: How were our plots and correspondence with <hi>Biron</hi> carryed▪ with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite the like examples.</p>
            <p>Touching the latter, the Spanish Nation hath of all other in the world beene held for the most sober, stayd, and wise, and were wont neuer to attempt any thing but vpon great and long aduice, accounting it with <hi>Quintus Fabius</hi> more honorable to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted droanes or cowards, then to hazard our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, or Armies, French like, onely in a vaine-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious hastinesse to gaine the Honor of charging the first. So that it seemeth strange to me that we haue I know not vpon what grounds incurred the hate and scorne of other Nations, and that we especially of the Nobility should be thought ill of since of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility ours of <hi>Spaine,</hi> hath beene euer held the most illustrious and eminent of the world.</p>
            <p>The Duke hauing made an end, <hi>Gondomar</hi> easily
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176797:5"/> raysing himselfe from his chayre wherein he sat vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on two downe pillowes, and resting himselfe vpon a little Brasill staffe, spake as followeth.</p>
            <p>My Lords, I can deriue this slaunder of our Country, and hate of our selues from no other fountaine then the Fanaticall humors and distracted spirits of some of the English, who find themselues not a little gall'd and vexed with our politique de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes heretofore, and now our finall reiection, and (I hope) shaking hands with that Hereticall Nation for euer, for if your Alteses and Honors will but consider what aduenture and boote we haue made by them, I thinke you will say we might well endure these British Northen and cold blasts: meane time in so suffering for our Catholique King, and in the Catholique cause we ought to take such approbry rather as an Honor vnto vs then otherwise.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, if we shall consider who are the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of these flying Plamphlets, wee shall finde to proceede from the pennes of light and vnstayed wits, with intent eyther to winne the opinion of good intelligencers and statistes together with the aiery applause of the Vulgar, or to rayse to their des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Fortunes, when the tempest is ouer, (as it oft hath happened) and now likely we being fallen off from <hi>England,</hi> and the Treaty at an end.</p>
            <p>Yea, but quoth the Duke of <hi>Medina Caeli,</hi> what should be the reason of that inbred and Naturall hate the common people of <hi>England</hi> should beare to vs, and our Country aboue any Nation in the world, the <hi>Hollanders, Turkes,</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> excepted.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:176797:6"/>
            <p>Quoth the Arch-bishop of <hi>Toledo,</hi> herein we are<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arch. B.</hi> Toledo.</note> much deceiued, for his Catholique Maiesty and our selues all haue very many faithfull and fast friends in <hi>England,</hi> who would not sticke to hazard their liues and fortunes in the Seruice of his Maiesty, might time and occasion be offered, yea, and some none of the meanest.</p>
            <p>The Marquesse of <hi>Castello Rodrigo,</hi> then arising vp with a graue countenance, and a deliberate vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance sayd, is it possible that any place in the world should bring forth such a monster, as a Traytor to his Country, or allow bread to any one so vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally base, as to draw his sword, and side with an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy against her, I will say that for our <hi>Spaine,</hi> I do not remember or euer had read, that shee afforded a Traytor, or so much as one that serued a sworne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy against her Prince.</p>
            <p>By your fauour, quoth <hi>Lewes de Velasco,</hi> what Country-man was he of <hi>Count Iohn</hi> of <hi>Nassau's</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, that tooke the Admirant of <hi>Arragon</hi> priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at the battaile of <hi>Neuport.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true quoth <hi>Gonzales de Cordua,</hi> he was a Spaniard, but examples hereof are very rare.</p>
            <p>Quoth <hi>Gondomar,</hi> so they are, and though <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> be the colder Country, yet it hath bred more venemous Creatures of this Nature, then euer <hi>Spaine,</hi> yea euen vnder the Sunne-shine of their mildest and most moderate gouernments.</p>
            <p>Whence quoth the Duke of <hi>Escalona</hi> should this proceede.</p>
            <p>I will tell you (quoth <hi>Gondomar</hi>) my opinion,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176797:6"/> the English naturally are desirous of nouelties, and innouations, and as it were sicke in the soft beds of their long liberty, peace, and plenty, (which they enioy vnder as wise and as good a King as euer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) they suppose nothing wanteth to their full hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse but change and variety: I must liken them to <hi>Giotto</hi> of <hi>Florence</hi> his Asse, who when he went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with a rich saddle of beaten gold on his backe with a Crowne and Scepter lying thereon, yet he could not choose but smell vpon a Carriers packe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saddle as it lay at an Inne doore.</p>
            <p>Hence are strangers the most admired and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayned amongst them, and if of quality preferred many times to place and preferment before the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, though perhaps there are many who deserue better. I haue seene there a torne and tatter'd French Lacquay, but as this day arriued out of <hi>France,</hi> and the next, he hath ietted in the Court in his Tissue or Scarlet at the least: what preferment came that arch-hypocrite <hi>Spalato</hi> vnto. <hi>Ascanio</hi> the Frier, who left his wife in St. <hi>Mantins</hi> lane, and ranne againe to his Order. And a poore and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Italian Mountebanke, sought after for his skill as if <hi>Aesculapius</hi> or <hi>Machaon</hi> were againe rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed from the dead, yea when but a Spanish gowne (happily of the Embassadours Lady, or of her gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman) how was it sought after by Ladies, and Taylors for the fashion, happy was she that could first get her into the Spanish fashion, to their no small charge, the Spanish garments exceeding all other in fulnesse, compasse, and length, which by this time it may be they haue conuerted into Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shions.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176797:7"/> My Lords, you would hardly haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne laughter, to haue heard how I haue beene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired after for Maisters for the Spanish tongue, (that I may say nothing of so many bills set vp in euery corner of the City by Professors) nay I could haue no seruice almost done me of my Mullettors and Groomes, for being employed in teaching the Spanish among Ladyes and their maydes, though I knew I tell you, English must be that they were to trust too when all was done.</p>
            <p>Touching my selfe being Embassadour there from his Catholique Maiesty, and the sole instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Treaty for the match, which the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques there so long thirsted after, if I should relate vnto you the particulars of mine owne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, you would (I suppose) imagine I told you wonders beyond beleefe, for beside the great and gracious respect I found, and fauors I receiued from his Maiesty of Great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> and sundry of the Nobility, who seemed wholy to be compounded of curtesie and Noblenesse, there passed not a day wherein I was not visited, by some of the best ranke, or receiued some present or other, from Catholique Gentlemen, or their Ladyes, (so welcome was the very thought of the Spanish match vnto them) I returning them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, with thankes, large promises, and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant hopes of preferment, when the time should come.</p>
            <p>And be it spoken among our selues, since wee are falling off from <hi>England,</hi> I made better vse of their kindnesse then so, for there were few Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:176797:7"/> in <hi>England</hi> of note, from whom in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, I wrested not out a good round summe of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: Sir <hi>Robert Cotton</hi> a great Antiquary, I heare, much complaineth of me, that from his friends and aquaintance onely I got into my purse the summe at the least of ten thousand pounds, I deny it not; and true it is, I borrowed of the good old Lady <hi>W.</hi> of the Parish in St. <hi>Martins</hi> in the Feilds 300 pounds, or thereabouts, promising her repayment (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I will not faile) so soone as <hi>Donna Maria,</hi> the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta</hi> should arriue in <hi>England,</hi> and for the vse here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I promised to make her mother of her maydes, perswading her, it was not fit that so graue and good a Lady as her selfe should lye obscured in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, but rather attend vpon my young Mistresse, the brauest and most hopefull Princesse of the World, vpon these hopes she turned Catholique, and since I neuer saw her. I sold moreouer, the place of Groo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>messe, of her highnesse Stoole, to six seuerall Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Ladyes, who were eager of it, only cause be they might take place before their fellowes: I lost nothing neither by a Noble Gentleman, whom I caused to be knowne for a kinsman of the King my Mr. for that he was descended from the Noble and ancient fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Aiala</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> these are but mites and crums in regard of those great presents, and many pentions I had sent me vnder-hand, from the Catholiques from all parts of <hi>England</hi> during my aboade there, had my finger but aked, or beene ill disposed (as I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten was in body) I had sent me iewels, sweet-meates, perfumes, linnen, Rose-water, and a thousand of such trifles, only I returned them thankes, and promised them or their friends preferment, when time serued.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:176797:8"/>
            <p>If you were my Lord, so nobly entertained in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> quoth <hi>Braganza,</hi> whence is it, or vpon what occasion haue wee gotten to our selues the ill will and distast of that Nation.</p>
            <p>I must confesse, quoth <hi>Gondomar,</hi> the common people of <hi>England</hi> beare generally an inbred spleene toward vs, as it seemeth by many rude affronts, we were offered there by the baser sort, contrary to the will and pleasure of his Maiesty of great <hi>Brittany,</hi> who published many Edictes and Proclamations in our behalfes, punishing many times the offenders seuerely as they could be taken, but why the name of a <hi>Spaniard</hi> should be so become odious vnto them, is a question I cannot easily resolue.</p>
            <p>Some thinke that there is a naturall antipathy or contrariery of affection betweene our disposition and theirs, they liuing in the North, and we in the South; which being (as <hi>Charron</hi> a French Author obserueth) neerer to the Sunne, the inhabitants are more crafty, politique, and religious, (though he his in that) euen to superstition and Idolatry, where as on the contrary, those of the North (howsoeuer goodlier in person, better faced, and more beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then our selues by reason of the coldnesse of the climate, preseruing inwardly the naturall heate, and radicall moysture,) are plaine simple, nothing so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious contemners withall, of the glorious cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of our Church, wherewith we haue drawne more Heathen in eyther India to Christianity, in one yeare, then they can with their Lutheran and Caluinisticall Sermons in all their liues.</p>
            <p>This very selfe same thing (quoth <hi>Gonzales</hi>) I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176797:8"/> once vrged by way of Argument to an Earle of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> who was a professed Lutheran Heretique, and his reply herein was, so are fooles and children taken with bells, gilt pouches, and colours, and our Ladies and faire Gentlewomen, (we see) oftentimes woed and wonne, only with a braue out-side on the backe of a base knaue, when an honest man, and of deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing parts is reiected, in a plaine and ordinary suite of clothes, and not held worthy the looking after.</p>
            <p>They talke as they are (quoth <hi>Gondomar</hi>) I am sure these drew more to my little priuate Chappell in <hi>Holborne,</hi> then their best Preachers of Sermons could doe to any Church they had.</p>
            <p>But quoth the Duke of <hi>Hijaz,</hi> it may be they hate vs for the same cause, that <hi>France, Germany, Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi> and the rest of the Countries of <hi>Europe,</hi> for that many of vs are discended of the Moorish race: wherefore we are termed of them in <hi>Italy, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rani,</hi> and of other <hi>Moros Blancos,</hi> and <hi>Nue vos Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos:</hi> For indeede it was but in the yeare 1492. when <hi>Granado</hi> was recouered from the Moores, <hi>Mahomet</hi> sirnamed the Little, and sonne of <hi>Muley Albohacen</hi> being King thereof, though <hi>Toledo</hi> and <hi>Cordoua</hi> long before, and it may be they hold vs still infected with Moorish minds, and a spice of their manners, though they are assured we are Christians, yea and the most Catholique too.</p>
            <p>I heare (quoth Signior <hi>Gondomar</hi>) it is obiected in their now present Parliament, that in all treatises for the space of these two hundred yeares, <hi>Spaine</hi> hath dealt with the English, <hi>fide punica,</hi> neuer kept
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176797:9"/> touch with them in any serious capitulation, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer aiming at her owne ends, vsed their alliance and friendshippe but as a stale or stalking-horse ouer their backes to shoote at others, or serue her owne necessities for the present, and hereof their Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaries (they say) haue found many Presidents. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others they affirme and proue, to the preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of our Treaty, that <hi>Charles</hi> the fift was first him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe betrothed to Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> and I know vpon what tricke and policy he vntied himselfe againe, and vsed the meanes to conferre her vpon Prince <hi>Philip</hi> his sonne.</p>
            <p>But the very truth is, they carry a vindictiue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution against vs euer since our intended conquest of them in 88. and peraduenture the Powder-plot in 1605. which yet seemeth <hi>Manere alta mente repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum.</hi> Indeede <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. of <hi>France,</hi> sirnamed the <hi>Great,</hi> laboured at one time a reconciliation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs, but he found the rootes of eithers discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent so deepe, and the sore so vnsalueable, that hee gaue it ouer in the end. Touching mine owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, I was generally hated, I confesse, of the common people: for no other cause, I imagine, then for the great grace and fauour I was in with his Maiesty, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom I had free accesse at all times, and his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious eare to any reasonable suite or request I could demaund, the particulars of the Seruice I did to the King my Master (whom God long preserue) I thinke are not vnknown vnto you, I omitting no one houre or minute of time wherein I did not benefit either him by my seruice, my selfe by experience, or a friend by a good turne.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:176797:9"/>
            <p>For during the time of my abode in <hi>England,</hi> and whilest I lay in <hi>London,</hi> I got partly by the meanes of well affected friends, and partly by mine owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience (for in sommer, time vnder the colour of taking the ayre, I would take view of the countrey) I had perfect knowledge of the estate of the whole Land: for there was no Fortification, Hauen, Creeke, or Landing-place about the Coast of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but I got a platforme and draught thereof, I learned the depth of all their Channels, I was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with all Sands, Shelues, Rockes, Riuers that might impeach or make for inuasion, I had perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually in a Role the names of all the Ships of King <hi>Iames</hi> his Nauy Royall, I knewe to a haire of what burthen euery ship was, what Ordinance she carried, what number of Saylors, who were the Captaines, for what places they were bound, which were in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire and fit for seruice, and which not, I knew the strength of the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> what Armour, Ordinance, small Shot and Powder it might affoord. You know moreouer my Lords, I acquainted the King my maister with Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh's</hi> inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded voyage to <hi>Guiana,</hi> and euery particular thereof, when it was but in embryone, and when he himselfe vowed onely three were acquainted with his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose and resolution, but the fourth should neuer know what he intended vntill he had set footing in <hi>America:</hi> yet I say, I knew what he aimed at, what course he meant to hold, where to land, what places he meant to surprise, what force he carried, and by what way he resolued to returne: with all which particulars, as I haue already sayd) I acquainted you
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176797:10"/> long ere he went, and he was no sooner gone but I was assured I had his head at my deuotion, to take it when I listed (hauing sufficient matter to all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him) and at last, though his treason for which he stood condemned many yeares before) was the hatcher, yet the hand was mine that gaue him the blow: For it concerned vs aboue all the rest in case we should fall off from <hi>England,</hi> and burst out into our old enmitie, to make away with him, who would haue proued the onely Boutefeu and Cendiarie of the world, instirring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p the hatred of the <hi>English</hi> and other Nations against vs, he being a Darling of our late deadliest enemy Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and one of the last men to be borne of those great Spirits, and experienced Captaines the time of her raigne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. His Maiesty (I humbly thanke him) tooke e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially notice of this seruice of mine (and as it was told me) gaue me great thankes for it aboue the rest.</p>
            <p>I was no lesse diligent for the discouery of the Inland, then for the Shores and Sea-coasts: For there was neu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r a Sheire in <hi>England,</hi> but I better know the estate, power and quality thereof then the Inhabitants, euen the best of them themselues did. I could in particular relate the nature of the soyle, what power of men and horse th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y were able to raise, who were the chiefe and of most ability and credit in the Countrey, who the most antient Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, what they were worth in their reuenues and estates, how they stood affected in Religion, who were Puritanes, and who Catholiques, and among Catholiques who stood for vs, and who (for such
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176797:10"/> there were) were indifferent or against vs. And which moreouer is of equall consequence, there was not a Sermon preached at <hi>Paules</hi> Crosse, or indeed in any other Church of the City or place in the Kingdome, that did but touch the hemme of my maisters gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or was any way preiudiciall vnto vs or the match (which we seemingly intended) but I had my Leame-hounds ready in euery corner to draw after them dry-foote, and fetch the Authors <hi>Coram nobis,</hi> to their cost, as one Dr. <hi>Euerard</hi> of St. <hi>Martins,</hi> was for his bold and malapert inueighing and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally preaching against vs and the match silenced by my onely meanes, for (I sayd) and often told my best friends, till the mouthes of such <hi>Rabshecahs</hi> were stopped, no vnitie or sincere reconciliation of either Nation: (for the effecting of which now was the time) could possibly be expected. One <hi>Whiting,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides a Dr. of Diuinity, Mr. <hi>Clayton</hi> for his <hi>Spanish Ewe,</hi> in a Sermon at S. <hi>Paules</hi> Crosse was layd vp for his lauish tongue, and had like before to haue smar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a Sermon hee made before his Maiestie at <hi>Wansted</hi> in <hi>Essex</hi> in <hi>August</hi> some two yeares since, taking for his Text, <hi>Remember Lots Wise, Luk.</hi> 17. 32. And I thinke <hi>Ward</hi> of <hi>Ipswich</hi> escaped not safely for his lewd and profane picture of 88. and their Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der treason, one whereof my L. Arch-bishop I sent you in a letter, that you might see the malice of these detestable Heretiques, against his Holinesse and the Catholique Church.</p>
            <p>Neither was there any publicke speech made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly in any Court of Iustice, were it in either house of Parliament; Starre Chamber, Countrey Assize,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:176797:11"/> yea, many times vttered priuately in the Court, but I got an inckling, and made good vse thereof: yea, I was partaker of Gossips newes in the Citty, brought to mine owne bed chamber by my wel knowne and priuate friend, &amp;c. Mrs. <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Fleet-streete.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeede Signior <hi>Gondomar,</hi> quoth one, herein consisted the pythe and marrow of your seruice, but if you please proceed.</p>
            <p>I againe entertained, to my no small charge, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligencers in euery Countrey (indeed Catholicke Priests) whose liberty out of prison I obtained for that very purpose: for being abroad, they did vs a threefold seruice: First they gained soules to God, friends to the King my maister, and money good store into our purses: for I got out of <hi>English</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques to mine owne vse threescore thousand pounds at the least.</p>
            <p>For the first, it hath bene certified me for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, &amp; by report from many of their own mouthes, that the number of soules which they haue gained into the bosome of the Church since the remission of the penall Lawes against them, and their freedom by my meanes obtained, amounteth to the number of eight and thirty thousand and odde.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they haue confirmed the Catholicks, and made them so fast for the King our Maister, that they haue auowed vnto me diuerse times, that rather then misse of the Match, they would make vp the best part of the <hi>Infanta's</hi> portion out of their owne purses, yea, though it were with the selling or paw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all their plate and Iewels.</p>
            <p>Within the City, for a small matter, I feede
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176797:11"/> certaine discontented and necessitous Catholickes of the <hi>English,</hi> to walke the common and most fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented places of the Citty of <hi>London,</hi> as St. <hi>Paules</hi> Church, the Exchange, now and then among the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaries, to learne the common newes, out of which many times I picked good matter.</p>
            <p>Neither could the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> or the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadors of any other Forraine Prince carry their businesse so close, but with my Maisters golden Key, I could finde a meanes to diue into their Cabbinets, reseale and seale againe their Packets, without the helpe eyther of <hi>Arthor Gregory,</hi> or his old acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance <hi>Phillips.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was not one of my worst peeces, to hold the English in suspence, with an apparent ouerture of the match, and a dilatory promise of golden moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, with the age of old <hi>Saturne</hi> againe, when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery oake in <hi>Greenewich</hi> Parke, <hi>Sudaret roscida mella,</hi> till the <hi>Palatinate</hi> was lost beyond recouery, a matter of maine consequence: for hereby <hi>Bohemia</hi> with the rest of the Emperours Territories being secured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, our Maister may at pleasure call to his ayde the Emperors forces (who it seemeth for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose hath made a League with the <hi>Turke</hi> for these twenty yeares) together with the strength of <hi>Tilley,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Die Caese ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</note> and the D. of <hi>Bauaria</hi> ioyned, and with his own forces suddainly (for now is the time) giue <hi>Holland</hi> such a Camisado, as the best wits of the <note n="*" place="margin">So the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard scorn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cals the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ge where the States vsually reside.</note>
               <hi>Chiefe Chamber,</hi> will be to seeke of their old-ward, and wonted policy.</p>
            <p>Yea (quoth <hi>Don Pedro</hi>) but imagine this plot were resolued vpon, shall we thinke the Princes of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:176797:12"/>
               <hi>Germany,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> and other their old friends and allyes, will stand still as idle Spectators, and not runne in with their swords drawne to their rescue? Or that the <hi>Hollander</hi> who hath beene so long weather beaten at sea, is not able to discerne this storme a farre off, and take in his Sayles ere it shall hazard his Shippe, yes without doubt; and howsoeuer we may flatter our selues with the easinesse of the Conquest, wee shall assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly finde it as hard a taske as euer <hi>Spaine</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke.</p>
            <p>It is true, you say (quoth the Admirant of <hi>Castile</hi>) what haue we gained of them for these fifty yeares pace and vpward, euer since <hi>Don Iohn</hi> of <hi>Austria,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Alva, Lewes Requesens,</hi> were Gouernors, and vndertooke the Low-Country Warres, but sound knockes, with the fruitlesse ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of many a million.</p>
            <p>Quoth (<hi>Lewes de Velasco</hi>) a shorter cut for the<note place="margin">The error of the Duke of <hi>Alva.</hi>
               </note> Conquest of those Rebells, had beene long since ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, had the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> beene so wise as to haue secured himselfe of <hi>Brill, Flushing,</hi> and the rest of the Frontier, and Sea-Townes, he then might haue beene Maister of all the rest within at his pleasure, for so long as they were open and free, they were to the others, as the mouth to the stomacke or body, which could not possibly famish, so long as it was supplied continually from <hi>England,</hi> and other places, but this by the way.</p>
            <p>All what (quoth <hi>Gondomar</hi>) I haue already said is but a <hi>praeludium</hi> or small Preface, to those pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects I had in my braine, if (as vnluckily it hapned)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:176797:12"/> the Treaty had not suddainly broken off, but beene spunne out a yeare or two longer, which indeede was the maine plot, and had beene effected, had not<note place="margin">The Prince in <hi>Spaine</hi> before he was looked for.</note> the comming ouer of Prince CHARLES in Person into <hi>Spaine,</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> spoyled all, for howsoeuer we made a seeming shew of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing at his comming, and did him all Honor beseeming so great and worthy a Prince, yet to speake the truth my Lords, you all know wee wished him a thousand miles off; and I beleeue some of the English themselues were here sorry that he had enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himselfe in so long and teadious a iourney.</p>
            <p>But quoth the Duke of <hi>Hijaz</hi> standing vp and turning himselfe to the Duke of <hi>Medina Coeli,</hi> and the Archbishop of <hi>Toledo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How may it be conceiued that the Prince of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> his arriuall in <hi>Spaine,</hi> should either praeiudice vs, or the Treaty of the Match a whit, since he found here the greatest content he could deuise, he had a sight of the Lady <hi>Maria la Infanta</hi> his Mistresse, whose selfe knowne and seene exceeded her same, he was entertained and attended vpon by the most compleate and generous Nobles of <hi>Europe,</hi> and had that entertainment, no Nation could affoord the like. Lastly, <hi>Maiorem habemus fidem ijs quae oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis vsurpamus, quam quae auribus haurimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quoth the Duke of <hi>Escalonia,</hi> the effect hath fallen out quite contrary, for the English report since their comming home, they neuer came into a baser Country in their liues, where they could get<note place="margin">Great want of victuall and prouision in <hi>Spaine▪</hi>
               </note> meate neither for themselues or their horses, nor saw so much as one handfull of grasse in two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:176797:13"/> miles riding, and if they dined at one place,<note place="margin">He that surfets at a Spaniards Table, trust me I will pay for his physicke.</note> they were faine to go 30 or 40 miles ere they could get any thing to their supper, and then perhaps a peece of leane Kid, or Cabrito, a Tripe, Tone's or such like, indeede I remember when the Prince lay at <hi>Madrid,</hi> we were faine to send seauenteene miles off for a Calfe, for his highnesse Dyet, as for Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton we may kill none without especiall Licence from the King, for fish our Riuers affoord none, and we being most temperate our selues, how should our dyet agree with their stomackes, who are accounted the greatest feeders of the World.</p>
            <p>I verily beleeue indeede (quoth <hi>Gondomar</hi>) that those places they call in <hi>England,</hi> East-cheape, and Smith-field Barres, kills, and vtters more Beefe and Mutton in a month, then all <hi>Spaine</hi> eates in seauen yeares, which plenty our men meeting withall, at our first comming ouer into <hi>England;</hi> and since some who attended <hi>Don Iniosa</hi> (as I lately heard) did ouer eate themselues, and died shortly after.</p>
            <p>The poore and miserable surface of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; (quoth <hi>Escalona</hi>) the scarcity of victuall and<note place="margin">The Princes going ouer in person, was happy for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> hardnesse of lodging was not all, the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> by comming in Person discouered our plot, and found how faire so euer wee pretended, wee meant nothing lesse, when he thinking (as also did the King of Great <hi>Brittaine</hi> his father) nothing had beene wanting to the absolute consummation of the marriage, but the Rites of the Church, he found all as Raw and as backward, as hee had beene all this while in a Dreame, and no such matter euer thought of: So that he found the Honor of our glorious
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:176797:13"/> entertainment to be but as a delicate sawce to helpe digestion.</p>
            <p>The Marques of <hi>Castello Rodrigo</hi> then stepping vp, sayd, I will adde one thing more, and whereof if he liues, he vowes not to be vnmindfull of; and that is as I am inform'd, some affronts done him by the Clergy, as that rude and barbarous putting him<note place="margin">Adde more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vp of the bodies of our buried dead, casting them into the Sea.</note> out of a Church which his Highnesse came in to view: The arresting and taking away of a young youth a Page, who attended, (I thinke) on Maister <hi>Mounteague</hi> in a manner from his heeles, which young Gentleman (they say) cannot be heard of to this day; with that (insolent and african pride) of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strayning him from that liberall accesse and conuerse, (not denied elsewhere to a meane person) with the Lady <hi>Maria Infanta</hi> his Mistresse (which Princes by their his owne right may challenge, he being equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent in birth, and the rarest endowments of body and minde, to any Prince whatsoeuer in the world) with whom in all the time of his being here, he had not aboue twice talked, and then before eyther the Queene. or your selfe Signior <hi>Olivares</hi> or some other, if he had any thing to say afterward, it was by vs to be penned to his hand, and to be spoken before witnesse, we must assuredly thinke and expect that so great and eminent a Prince, and the darling of that Nation, howsoeuer he could wisely smoother his discontent amongst vs in <hi>Spaine,</hi> we may one day perhaps finde the fruites of our double dealing, and the effects of his haught and incensed courage, well knowing how, like a young Lyon, though yet in his Denne, and scarce acquainted with ranging, his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:176797:14"/> teeth and nayles are growne to that length, that he is past iesting or playing withall.</p>
            <p>Indeede my L. <hi>Olivares,</hi> you are much blamed for that discouery and light you gaue to <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Infanta by her Fathers will, bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed to the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perors Sonne.</note> of our designe, and the secret and tenor of the last Kings will, wherein he charged vs not to match with <hi>England,</hi> but rather to hold a faire Treaty with them, hauing as you all know bequeathed <hi>Maria</hi> the <hi>Infanta</hi> to the Emperours sonne, so that now the English suppose themselues manifestly deluded.</p>
            <p>Quoth the Duke of <hi>Sesa,</hi> they know it well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and I beleeue we shall finde them so sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it, that we had beene better to haue played faire, then to hazard the loosing of our rest by such an encounter.</p>
            <p>Now I pray you let vs take into our considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the mischiefes which are like to follow.</p>
            <p>First, it is thought hereupon they haue called a Parliament, which consisteth of the King, Prince, all the Lords Spirituall, and Temporall, of the Gentry, and Commons of the ablest iudgements, and vnderstanding in the Land, vnto this Parliament: the King (they say) hath wholy referred himselfe, not onely for the examination and redresse of all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buses and misdemeanors at home, but for the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussing and searching into all plots and practises of<note place="margin">The vnity and sweet consent of the King &amp; his people in this present Parliament ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>serued.</note> others abroad, that may seeme any way to preiudice the quiet and well gouerned estate of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, without interposition or mediation, so that the King and people go all on and together, with that alacrity and constancy, in prouiding for the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176797:14"/> good estate of the Kingdome, as the like hath not beene seene these many yeares, Prince CHARLES himselfe being there earely and late, <hi>Assiduvs &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubuus,</hi> amongst them, whom (I am informed) with the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> wee haue our prime and principall opposers.<note place="margin">A difference betweene the Duke of <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingham,</hi> and Count <hi>Olivares</hi> which the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists giue out (though falsly) to be the first occasion of the breach of the match.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I must confesse (quoth <hi>Count Olivares</hi>) there fell a difference betweene the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and my selfe, which some haue rashly and inconside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately giuen out, to be the onely cause of this breach, for they say before that time all things went forward in as faire a way as might be.</p>
            <p>Indeede quoth <hi>Toledo</hi> the Catholiques of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> haue so giuen it out, laying all the fault vpon the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> who is not guilty of any such thing, I will excuse him, that peece was ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mered vpon our owne Anuile: <hi>Buckingham</hi> is a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Wise, and a Generous Prince, vpon whom the King his Maister hath deseruedly conferred his grace, and those transcendent Honors, yea though for no other former merit else then the resolute and wise carriage of himselfe, in the businesse of this Treaty amongst vs, whereby he hath not onely assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himselfe of the affection and heart of the King and Prince, but infinitely for his faithfull seruice, (another <hi>Fidus Achates</hi>) vnto him gained the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall loue of the Common people, as it not long since appeared, when he was ill after his tedious Voyage by Sea, (The Prince himselfe all the time healthy and sound) for whose returne the people had beene excessiue, and beyond measure, had it not beene somewhat allayd, and tempered with the report
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:176797:15"/> of <hi>Buckinghams</hi> sicknesse, they praying as heartily<note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> for his true seruice to the King &amp; Prince, and State▪ heartily beloued of the people.</note> for his recouery, as if he had beene some good land-Lord, or great House-keeper amongst them, whose losse had beene halfe their vndoing.</p>
            <p>It were to be wished, quoth <hi>Don Mendosa,</hi> that the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and himselfe with the rest of the Parliament, were not vpon iust cause I confesse, so bent against vs. I remember, quoth the Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, when I was a young Student, a saying of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca, Ingenuitas non recipit contemptum, Ingenuitie</hi> or a generous spirit can in no wise brooke contempt, shall we imagine then a Prince, yea such a Prince as CHARLES of <hi>Wales,</hi> and onely Sonne to the King of Great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> vpon whom and whose action's as a bright blazing Comet <hi>Europe</hi> begins to fixe her eye, affraid and doubtfull, where the fatall effect of his discontent will light, will carry coales, and not cry quittance with his enemies, yet doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, his mettle is of another temper, and not so flexible as some take it; for mine owne part I would not haue him our enemy, if his friendship could be had, though with the expence of many millions of Ducates.</p>
            <p>As if <hi>Spaine,</hi> quoth <hi>Rodrigo,</hi> needed to feare that<note place="margin">Cujus contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um verum est.</note> angle of the world <hi>England,</hi> haue not we euermore giuen them their hands full? haue they not more fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our Fleetes and Armies, then we theirs? do we not equal them in men, and expert Commanders, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well by land as by sea? do we not exceede them in Treasure, and money from our <hi>Indian</hi> mines? that like euer▪ running Fountaines, are neuer drawne dry, that I may say nothing of the courage of our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176797:15"/> our wisedome and pollicy whereby wee haue made our selues maisters of so many goodly Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, and gained so many braue victories both at Sea and Land.</p>
            <p>Had we an enemy, quoth the D. of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a,</hi> of farre lesse ability and power then <hi>England</hi> is, we ought not so slightly to contemne him, the wofull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence<note place="margin">A quarrell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a load of Calues skins cost the D. of <hi>Burgundy</hi> the losse of his life &amp; whole estate.</note> whereof our Nation naturall haughty and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionate of their valour, as well as others haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> out of aninsolent pride so contemned the <hi>Swisses,</hi> the quarrell arising betwixt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m but for the tole of a load of Calues skinnes; that at the last by them, he was depriued both of his estate and life, at that vnfortunate encounter at <hi>Nancie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Spaniards pride and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of vs, how deare it cost them at <hi>Neuport.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Who could with-hold the Arch-duke <hi>Albertus,</hi> and our grand Captaines from bidding Prince <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice</hi> battle at <hi>Neuport:</hi> But scorning the enemy in regard of his small number, in respect of theirs, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether being puffed vp with that petty victory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Scots</hi> the same morning, they had the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of pride and contempt of a weake aduersary, for the Arch-duke was forced to flye; sauing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe very hardly, leauing dead behind him, the oldest and best Souldiers <hi>Spaine</hi> had. Let vs beleeue the weakest may do vs a mischiefe, as is wittily showne by <hi>Aesop</hi> in that fable or apology of his betweene the Eagle and the Conies. But by your fauour my Lord, you are much mistaken in the estate and strength of <hi>England;</hi> and quality of the people, and so you will tell me, if wee shall haue to doe with them, as we haue found, and had in former times, let vs
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:176797:16"/> thinke two of the accession of <hi>Scotland</hi> vnto that Kingdome, and how <hi>Ireland</hi> standeth in good<note place="margin">The strength of <hi>Ireland</hi> at this present.</note> termes, and is at this time so well peopled with English and Scottish, that there is not so much as a starting hole left for Rebellion, or so much ground to spare in that Country, that might affoord any friends horse of ours a bottle of Hay, muchlesse suffice for an army to march ouer, and to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained vpon.</p>
            <p>I might hereto adde the valour and sufficient fidelity of that Noble Gentleman, Sir <hi>Henry Carie</hi> Lord Viscount <hi>Falkland,</hi> the now present Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty thereof, with many other braue Spirits, that are imployed in his Maiesties seruice in that good Country.</p>
            <p>But to returne to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> what effects heare you is it likely to produce, or wherein is it thought to prooue praejudicious to the King our Maister, or to the Catholique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?</p>
            <p>First replyed <hi>Gondamor,</hi> it is likely to goe worse with the Catholiques then euer, as who must ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no fauour, but must prepare themselues to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the sharpest censure, and animaduersion of the Law against them, yea whosoeuer shall be found abettors, maintainors, concealors of their plots or harberours of their persons, shall suffer for the same in like manner; and I heare say, that there is a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation eyther comming foorth, or published al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to that effect, and how they are to depart the Realme by a prefixed day.</p>
            <p>But what (quoth Count <hi>de Monterey</hi>) will then
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:176797:16"/> become of them, or by whom shall they be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained? will they returne to their Colledges againe<note place="margin">The Seminary Colledges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, almost empty at this time.</note> at <hi>Doway, Rhemes, Roome, Villadolid,</hi> and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, some whereof I haue lately seene, and obserue to stand empty.</p>
            <p>Nothing lesse (quoth <hi>Gondomar</hi>) for I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded though many wil colourably depart though returne againe shortly by new ports and new names moe will remaine behind, (and since neuer likely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to haue such an opportunity of professing themselues openly, and exercising their functions, which they could do in a friends Chamber, and many times in the common Innes) for the better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyding suspition, and concealing themselues, some will turne Schoole-maisters in priuate mens houses, as there are many in <hi>England,</hi> some Gentlemen Vs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers vnto Collapsed Ladies are, some such there are in <hi>Drury</hi>-lane: the L. T. in <hi>Yorkeshire,</hi> hath one fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes her in that Nature; the L. S. not farre from my old house in <hi>Holborne</hi> in <hi>London;</hi> the L. M. neere vnto <hi>Stratford-bow:</hi> Some <hi>Falconers</hi> whereof I know two, the one in <hi>Sussex,</hi> the other in high <hi>Suffolke,</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one I was acquainted withall, who was the Keeper of a Parke, and a good Huntsman, and of whom I haue had many a good peece of Venison, if he be liuing, I know another Priest who hauing liued with an ancient Lady of great estate, and of good credit, by reason he was enuironed with a pestilent crew of Puritanes on euery side, and the better to colour his absence from the Church, learned the arte of Cookery, and is growne so expect therein, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a short space, that hee is able to dresse a Dinner
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:176797:17"/> with such arte, and good meate after the English fashion, that neuer a Cooke in all <hi>Spaine,</hi> is able to set the like by it, and his manner is, when hee hath layed his meate to the fire, to goe and say Masse, which finished by that time, or soone after his meate is boyled or roasted, which with a cleane Apron, and white sleeues with some small helpe of a kitchin boy, he serueth vp to his old Mistresse.</p>
            <p>Quoth the Arch-bishop, this was the condition of the old Christians, vnder the persecuting Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,<note place="margin">Erasinus.</note> of which times it is sayd; <hi>Ingeniosa res fuit illis temporibus esse Christianum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The number of Priests and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits in <hi>London</hi> only, is 255 in a manner fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery parish two if Masse were vp againe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Without doubt quoth <hi>Gondomar,</hi> they will be seuerely proceeded against in this present Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that for many respects.</p>
            <p>First, by reason of their number, and daily increase, whereby they became formidable to the State.</p>
            <p>Secondly, because of the correspondence they<note place="margin">God be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the house is well rid of them.</note> held with vs, for by their meanes we vnderstood the secrets of their State, knew what they did, or spake in their Parliaments, in a word, they were our onely instruments for any imployment, were it neuer so desperate.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, (wherein I must needes say, they were to blame) they abused the Kings grace, and Lenity towards them, with their insolency and affronts oft<note place="margin">The Kings Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity abused.</note> times brauing their Aduersaries in the streetes to their faces, Preachers in their Pulpits, Iudges and Iustices on the Bench, that had they so done with vs in <hi>Spaine,</hi> they should haue soundly smarted for it, of what Religion soeuer they had beene.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:176797:17"/>
            <p>For example, vpon <hi>Easter</hi> monday last, in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-noone, came a Iesuite formally attired in blacke<note place="margin">Aske Maister <hi>Primrose</hi> of the truth hereof.</note> to the Court, then at White Hall (the day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being the day of the Kings healing of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sease, they call there, the Kings euill, what time a great throng of people of all sorts being gathered together, at the doore of Serieant <hi>Primrose,</hi> who was to take the names, and to search such as had neede of helpe) thrust into the Chamber, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demaunded what businesse he had there, faining himselfe to be in drinke made answere hee had none, neither knew he how hee came there; they seeing him in such a case, would haue carried him into another roome, and haue layd him vpon a bed, but he refused it, and hearing by chance Mr. <hi>Primrose,</hi> and one Mr. <hi>White</hi> conferre in Latine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, he suddainly brake out, and sayd, know you not such a one who attendeth vpon such a Lord, he is my Brother and a Catholique, whereat Mr. <hi>White</hi> replied I pray get you gone, I care for no such com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, where vpon he would haue drawne his dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and had not company been nigh, he had doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse slaine him; and no sooner was hee out of the Chamber, but he returned with three or foure more of his friends and acquaintance, daring him to come forth, and deeply vowing to be reuenged vpon him, and the rest within, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, because (say the English) they are the<note place="margin">No treason commonly without a Priest or Iesuit at on end of it.</note> only engines and complots of all Treasons, authors of Tumults, and seditious within the land, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance long since the rebellion in the North, of late the Gun-powder Treason, <hi>Watsons</hi> plot with that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:176797:18"/> of Sr. <hi>Walter Raleighes,</hi> and many more the like.</p>
            <p>Fift and lastly, because their carriage not answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the reuerend and high dignity of their professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they are growne odious (say they) to those euen of their owne side, for indeede they are the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly boone Companions about the Towne, loosing hereby much of their valew, which I like not of. St. <hi>Francis</hi> was reputed so holy a man, that the Popes<note place="margin">After the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> you are to licke your lippes.</note> Holinesse ordained, that whosoeuer did but name St. <hi>Francis,</hi> he should licke his lippes after, so sweete and Saint-like was his life and conuersasion: Yet now I remember at my departure out of <hi>England,</hi> I gaue it some of them in charge, to get what they could, of whom, or by what meanes soeuer, because I foresaw their haruest would be short, and the money would stand vs all instead, for indeede the greatest part was at my deuotion, and to be employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as I saw cause.</p>
            <p>And this stirred vp one <hi>Gee</hi> an Apostate Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist to publish a pestilent and a malicious against the Priests and Iesuites, residing in and about <hi>London,</hi> wherein after hee hath discouered their practises, he setteth downe in a Catalogue at the end all their names, with the places of their lodging, what bookes they haue at any time published, with the names of Catholique Doctors of Physicke, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, to their no small disgrace, and praeiudice.</p>
            <p>The things my L. quoth <hi>Sesa,</hi> at your beeing in <hi>England,</hi> were by your meanes wont to be seuerely looked into, and punished.</p>
            <p>It is true, quoth <hi>Gondomar,</hi> either hanging or losse of the Authors cares had ensued, or else I had
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:176797:18"/> missed of my ayme; but the case is now altered, I was then powerfull, and in grace, and by my pollicy ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected those things, which were they now to be wrought againe, would require the labour and all the strength of <hi>Hercules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my L. quoth the D. of <hi>Braganza,</hi> what newes lately from <hi>England,</hi> in what state stand things there, and how doth D. <hi>Intosa</hi> carry himselfe among the English, at this turbulent season, and amidst the deepest of their discontent, &amp; displeasure against vs?</p>
            <p>Well enough (quoth <hi>Gondomar</hi>) and the better if he be carefull to obserue some directions I gaue him, at my last departure, but for nouelty sake, I will produce a Letter I receiued from him, written with his owne hand, within these few dayes.</p>
            <p>My L. all health and happinesse euer attend our Soueraigne, his Catholique Maiesty, next your selfe<note place="margin">The Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against Priests and Iesuites.</note> and yours: You are much desirous I know to heare what the English Parliament hath already effected, or what they entend touching our selues, and the Catholiques, and the rather by your wisedome, that you might preuent further dangers, which if fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seene, are euer the better encountered withall, and withstood: Either house of Parliament with great vehemency against the Catholiques, hauing publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed a Proclamation for their finall banishment; and our selus euery day grow more odious &amp; in cōtempt with that Nation then other, which I cannot remedy, I did what lay in my power, and according to my direction, to breake off this Parliament, by laying an<note place="margin">So all the World sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth.</note> aspersion vpon the Prince, and D. of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> to breed a iealousie in the Kings Maiesty, which is hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nously taken of all the land, whereupon I hoped that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:176797:19"/> the Parliament would soone haue beene dissolued but my arte fayled me; and I haue gained nothing but disgrace, the enmity of the Prince and Duke, together with the hate of the whole Land, inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that your selfe S. <hi>Gondomar</hi> were wont to passe free and vnmolested, (except at once, or the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, when the offendors were imprisoned and punished) we cannot passe (though no violence I<note place="margin">The better sort neuer gaue you ill vse.</note> confesse is offered) but we haue the bans and reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of the multitude, I meane the baser sort, wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we had neuer come here.</p>
            <p>The diuell driue vs home againe, withall I had three or foure of the Proclamations for the bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of the Priests and Iesuites, pasted on my wall, hard by my doore: a Coachfull of my Gentlemen were by chance, hard by the <hi>Savoy</hi> ouerthrowne, but Lord what a shout was there among the multitude for ioy; some interpreting the same to be <hi>malum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> to our Nation, but <hi>Deo gratias</hi> there was no harme done.</p>
            <p>But are not these affrontes and vnseemely dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Common people with Embassadors, soundly punished.</p>
            <p>Yes indeede (quoth <hi>Gondomar,</hi>) it is much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his Maiesty, and the wall of the State, who by publique Proclamation, haue vpon a seuere pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty forbidden any whosoeuer, eyther by word or deede, to do them any affront or iniury, but it seems our dealing hath deserued it, how happeneth it then that these are not restrayned, replyed the M. of <hi>Mandesario.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is vnpossible (quoth <hi>Gondomar</hi>) to charme the tongues of a multitude, beside they are people of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:176797:19"/> the worser condition, for of the better sort we are respected with all obseruance: but let vs proceede<note place="margin">No Nation more benigne and curteous to strangers then English.</note> with the contents of my Lords Letter.</p>
            <p>Here came foorth about <hi>February</hi> likewise, a Proclamation for the banishment of all Priests, &amp;c. out of the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> but it is to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, that there be so many of the chiefe Magistrates and Gentlemen in <hi>Ireland,</hi> so well affected to the Catholique cause, that it will do vs no great hurt in those parts, though the cracke be terrible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Count Mansfield</hi> arriued not long since in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and had great entertainment, but what his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand or businesse was, I could neuer learne, though I tryed all the meanes I could to know, I am wanting in nothing insomuch as in some ingenious and good intelligencer. That (quoth <hi>Gondomar</hi>) is a fault which must be remedied, I remember of late yeares, there came a great personage, a messenger (call him Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassador I may not) from a Visier in <hi>Constantinople</hi>
               <note place="margin">A notorious practise of the Spaniards, to discouer the businesse of a Turkish Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassador with the estates, as the Hage in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> to the Estates of <hi>Holland,</hi> to the Hage, and there was sent from <hi>Antwerpe</hi> to insinuate into his acquaintaince, afterward into his seruice a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall borne Spaniard, who had beene formerly a slaue in CONSTANTINOPLE, and spake the the Turkish tongue, as naturally as if he had beene borne there, withall he knew the friends and kindred of the sayd Turkish Gentleman, and could call them by their names, and told him he was such a mans sonne of the City, who being taken Prisoner when he was young by the Spaniards, he was detayned as<note place="margin">Of the truth hereof enquire of Capt. I. B.</note> a Galley-slaue amongst them many yeares, and hauing now made an escape, fled to him for succour, and desired to serue him as an Interpreter, he belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:176797:20"/> all true that he sayd, entertayned him to attend on him in his Chamber, it fortuned that on a time when the Estates of <hi>North-Holland</hi> were inuited by the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to a Supper or Banquet at his Court in the <hi>Hage,</hi> and with them this Turkish Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassador, one of the Company a Dutch man, of <hi>North-Holland,</hi> obseruing his carriage and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and remembring that his garbe and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was Spanish, and moreouer avowing he had seene him in <hi>Spaine,</hi> caused him in despite of his new maister to be searched, and at the instant found about him directions how to carry himselfe, and which was the maine plot, to discouer what was the <hi>Turkes</hi> errand to the Estates, hereupon it being the time of Peace, he was banished, and at <hi>Delft</hi> put into a Boate and sent a way, vpon paine of his head neuer to returne into <hi>Holland</hi> againe: but these di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uises are like Stratagems in warre, once cluded ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be put in practise againe.</p>
            <p>Well to proceede, he writes vnto vs moreouer how and with what alacrite the Parliament with one<note place="margin">Prouision for making ready the Nauy.</note> consent haue granted Subsidies for furnishing and rigging vp the Nauy, and preparation for war.</p>
            <p>But writes he nothing, quoth <hi>Velasco,</hi> where it is thought they will appoint <hi>Sedem Belli,</hi> the home of that warre.</p>
            <p>That quoth <hi>Gondomar</hi> is a secret among them, but I thinke his Maiesty will reserue that to himselfe.</p>
            <p>Why quoth <hi>Lewes de Velasco,</hi> there should be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so secretly carried amongst them, but we should know it.</p>
            <p>The times (replyed <hi>Gondomar</hi>) are not now as heretofore, and when I was in <hi>England,</hi> our best in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligencers,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:176797:20"/> and the Catholiques are not in that grace as they haue beene: we haue had in times past many friends, euen in the Parliament House, but they haue now so sifted and cull'd them out, yea if but suspected that we haue little hope of diuing into their Actions.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> with the Estates of the Low-Countries, haue taken the same course, for whereas their entendments and resolutions, where and when to make a warre, was knowne in common to them all of the Councell, (so that what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined or concluded of, wee knew it the same night, or the next morning, witnesse the surprize of <hi>Breda</hi> with a turfe Boate, and their enterprize vpon <hi>Antwerpe</hi>) the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> reserues that within his owne brest, whereby things are now carried with farre more secrecy, and good successe then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.<note place="margin">The enterprise vpon <hi>Breda</hi> in <hi>Brabant.</hi>
               </note> But how happened it quoth <hi>C. Monterey</hi> that <hi>Breda</hi> (as I haue heard) was surprized notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>By meere accidents (quoth <hi>Gonzales de Cordua</hi>) for <hi>Antonio Lancavechia</hi> the Gouernour, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened not in seauen yeares before, lay that night from home (I meane the Castle) at <hi>Geertrudenberge</hi> sixe miles off, when the same night came letters vnto him from a friend, on the other side, which reuealed<note place="margin">The friend was suspected to be Mounsier <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neueit.</hi>
               </note> the plot, but leauing his sonne Deputy Gouernour he durst not open them (for vpon the opening once of a loue letter that came to his Father from a Lady, his Father charged him neuer to meddle with loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into any letter that was directed to him againe) but laying them vp till his Father came home, the Castle and Towne wherein were 5000. men horse and foot, with threescore and ten hidden close vnder
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:176797:21"/> turfes miraculously taken, the griefe whereof as some thinke, cost the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> his life.</p>
            <p>But quoth <hi>Castello Rodrigo,</hi> Signior <hi>Gondomar,</hi> if there remaine any more newes from <hi>England,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part it freely, we are I hope of one minde.</p>
            <p>Quoth the Arch-bishop of <hi>Toledo,</hi> I haue heard that since this little time of respite and freedome, wherein the Catholique Religion hath taken breath a little, there haue beene many miracles done in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes assuredly very many (quoth <hi>Gondomar</hi>) I heard it credibly reported for a truth, that St. <hi>Patricke</hi> visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly appeared to many Religious Priests and Friers at<note place="margin">This is as true as St. <hi>Francis</hi> eate a Spider, and scrathed her againe out of his thigh.</note> his Purgatory, confirming and preaching vnto them dayly, prophesing moreouer, a great time of perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution ere long to befall vpon them. Moreouer our Blessed Lady appeared to an English mayd, arraied as bright as the Sunne, with the Moone vnder her feete, whereupon she became wholy to be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Catholique.</p>
            <p>No doubt quoth the Duke of <hi>Medina Caeli,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of this Nature are meere impostures, what thinke you my L. Arch-bishop.</p>
            <p>No question, quoth <hi>Gonzales de Cordua,</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be perswaded that, that which they call the holy Blood of <hi>Boxall,</hi> which the <hi>Brabanders</hi> and all the Netherlands visit in Pilgrimage, and euery yeare lookes as red and fresh, as if it had beene taken from the body but yesterday, can be the very blood of Christ.</p>
            <p>Nor that a young married wife shall haue a child the same yeare if she can stride ouer at once Saint
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:176797:21"/>
               <hi>Rombauts</hi> breeches at <hi>Mechlin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor that as many of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> hold that <hi>Mary</hi> was buried at <hi>Hueclom,</hi> for which cause it hath beene in times past a place by Pilgrimes much fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented since we hold her Assumption into heauen, for quoth the Arch-bishop, Signior <hi>Gonzales</hi> these are <hi>Contraria in eodem obiecto,</hi> you are a Souldier, and you know for the most part they are none of the deuoutest men, I wish you rather modestly and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously with the Church, that all these things are true. Abuses may creepe in by accident, but neuer to be publickly allowed by the Sacred Authority of the Church.</p>
            <p>No, how chanced it (replied <hi>Gonzales</hi>) that a Painter of <hi>Shertogenbosch</hi> (my Lord of <hi>Grobbendonck</hi>
               <note place="margin">I my selfe haue often seen the picture, though neuer worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped it.</note> gouernour of the Towne, told me the tale) beeing deadly in loue with a faire and beautifull Lady neere to <hi>Pirroy Huesden,</hi> and being to drawe our Ladies Image for a Chappell, either in St. <hi>Iohns,</hi> or some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church in the <hi>Bosch,</hi> to insinuate himselfe the<note place="margin">The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> like one of her Images take off the golden coate of ceremony, vnderneath it is rubbish, or a rotten block:</note> farther into this Ladies fauour, drewe her picture with her young sonne in her armes, which he hung vp for our blessed Ladies picture, and is at this day worshipped with as great deuotion, as if her selfe were discended from heauen, and were there in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</p>
            <p>I cannot beleeue (quoth the Arch-bishop) there was any such thing, if there were) so long as it brings in good store of mony to the poore Priestes of the Church, it may easily be endured: besides, if these things should be ouer narrowly looked into, it would hazard the credit of the Catholicke Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:176797:22"/> to the vulgar and ignorant her greatest my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries, and as it were, pulling off her fairest plumes, expose her naked to vulgar scorne and contempt.</p>
            <p>But the D. of <hi>Escalono,</hi> who had sitten silent this good while, now stepping vp sayd, the end of our present assembly, is not to trouble our selues about these by discourses and triuiall matters, now it stands vs in hand to looke to our selues, to prouide money, men, and all necessaries for the warre withall speed, holding it fit to call home our Embassadour, who I beleeue hereafter is like to get no better answere concerning our affaires with <hi>England,</hi> then <hi>Mendo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> did of <hi>Henry Cary,</hi> Baron <hi>Hunsdon,</hi> and Lord <hi>Chamberlaine,</hi> in the dayes of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who beeing commanded by the Q. to giue him his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, she denying him accesse, by reason (say the English) his demaunds were insolent and vnreason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, told him the Queene hath commanded me to answere you, my answere is, <hi>Setting your Oranges and Limmons aside, a figge for your Embassage,</hi> his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was sauing for sause for their Hennes and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, they could liue, neither caring for vs, nor our Country.</p>
            <p>It seemeth (quoth <hi>Villa Hermosa</hi>) they care not<note place="margin">A Banquet sent out of <hi>Spaine</hi> to Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> not long since.</note> much for that neither, for when as a various and a delicate Banquet, such as <hi>Spaine</hi> afforded, was sent ouer, whether by your selfe my <hi>L. Olivares,</hi> your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or some other, to the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> I heard that the Prince touched not any whit of it, but the figges and other iunkettings were giuen some to one, some to another, and at last refused, euen of Boyes and Pages, for feare there should be dropped
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:176797:22"/> in a figge, or two worse rellished then their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Castello Rodrigo</hi> stood vp and sayd, Spice the English are so busie at home to prouide for themselues, and happily to offend some body else (whom yet we know not) let vs also timely prouide least we be to seeke, <hi>paries cum proximus ardet,</hi> and like true hearted Patriots and loyall Subiects to our Catholique King and Country, euery one sincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and freely deliuer his opinion, and reasons how our Religion, our selues, friends, and allyes might be best secured, in case the storme should fall on our heads, for this was the maine end of our meeting.</p>
            <p>Then quoth the Duke of <hi>Medina:</hi> Signior <hi>Gondomar,</hi> since you are best acquainted with the state and affaires of <hi>England,</hi> giue your aduise what is best to be done, whither to haue open warre with them, to wind them vp still with new pretences and ouertures of the Match, or to entertaine a (see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming) league of amity and vnity, and the <hi>Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> to take her Fortune else where.</p>
            <p>For the first, (quoth <hi>Gondomar</hi>) I vtterly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allow it, that we vpon no apparant ground, and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spaine</hi> vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be at oddes with <hi>England,</hi>
               </note> probable reason should prouoake so potent and irreconcilable a Nation, who are content to let vs alone, so that they may enioy their peace and quiet, you know the danger of awaking a sleepie Lyon, but hereof by the way, I will tell you a pretty and a pleasant accident of a sleepie dogge, that happened at my beeing in <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:176797:23"/> one <hi>D. W.</hi> well knowne about <hi>Paules</hi> and Feete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streete in <hi>London,</hi> (a place whereto I many times resorted) for some priuate occasion) finding his Dogge a great huge Mastiue lying fast a sleepe by<note place="margin">A tale of <hi>D. W.</hi> Dogge.</note> his Kitchin fire, sayd to a friend that stood by, my Dogge is fast a sleepe, I will (to wake him) go hallow in his eare, hee no sooner began to hallow, but the Dogge (vsed to no such alarmes) leapes vp, and laying his forefeete on his Maisters shoulders, tares him downe on eyther cheeke from the eyes, almost to the mouth: Let vs by no meanes hallow in the eares of the English, For first, we are not so well furnished with men, munition, or money, as the World imagineth, or <hi>Arse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls Magazines</hi> and Store-houses in <hi>Sevill, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diz, Lisbone,</hi> being almost disfurnished of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of munition and necessaries, though they seeme otherwise.</p>
            <p>How haue our Fleetes miscarried of late yeares, some by distresse and foulenesse of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spaine</hi> greatly endamaged of late yeares.</note> others by depredation and piracy of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> taken or sunke, Moreouer, consider how our eyther Indies (euen at this present) do <hi>Laborare in extremis,</hi> We neuer (since the first Conquest of the West by <hi>Columbus</hi>) in more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant daunger of loosing them, then at this time, by the great and vnexpected successe of the <hi>Hollander</hi> in those parts, yea within these few monthes.</p>
            <p>For the Fleete of <hi>Holland</hi> arriuing at <hi>Lima in Peru,</hi> eyther tooke or sunke the very best
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:176797:23"/> Shippes of our Nauy, or beaten the rest, so that they are vnfit for any seruice whatsoeuer, heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they haue now gotten footing (neuer knowne before) within that goodly and golden King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and by the assistance and courage of the Nauy Indians, (to whom the name of a Spaniard is more hatefull and odious then Hell) haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken many strong holdes and places of retract and defence, from whence they are not easily to<note place="margin">The <hi>Hollanders</hi> gotten footing in <hi>Peru</hi> this last yeare.</note> be vndermined, or remooued, their number and strength dayly encreasing, and they finding the commodity so great. For of all his Maiesties King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms in <hi>Europe, Asia,</hi> or <hi>America, Peru</hi> is the prime and Soueraigne, being aboue any other in the World, most abounding in gold, siluer, and pearle, where gold, and siluer is not as in other places, only with great labour, digged and sought for, in deepe and rockey mines, but here Nature hath disperst and throwne it about in such plenty, that it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily found in sands by the sea side, and vpon the common wayes, in wells, lakes, marishes, among stones in the earth, cleauing to the ground vnder the rootes of plants, and trees, plucked or digged vp, neither in scruples, or little and small graines, but in lumpes, and solid mashes, weighing two or three pound weight a peece.</p>
            <p>The like successe (we are certainly informed) they had but this other day (replyed the D. of <hi>Cea,</hi>) in going to the East-Indies vnder their Admirall <hi>Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits,</hi> by surprizing the strong Castle of <hi>Delr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io,</hi> which they yet hold and maintaine (hauing sent backe againe vnto <hi>Holland</hi> for a second Fleete to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:176797:24"/> their supply, which consisteth of 4000. marriners, whereof one ship (vnknowne to her fellowes) is fraught with handsome young wenches and boyes for plantation) these with the former making the number of fifty good ships, and for certaine it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that they are preparing for a third Nauie to follow the other two out of hand.</p>
            <p>I thinke (quoth L. <hi>De Velasco</hi>) the Diuell intends to giue them all the kingdomes of the earth.</p>
            <p>But replied the D. of <hi>Braganza,</hi> If I am not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,<note place="margin">Great prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Spaniards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander,</hi> but all in vaine.</note> they were met withall by the way, and fell farre short of their reckoning, to what end else should his Maiestie this last yeare prepare so mighty a Fleete, both in <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Portugall,</hi> sending for the ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of <hi>Dunkerke, Winoxbergen</hi> and <hi>Oostend:</hi> besides many merchant Ships arrested and stayed of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France, Lub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k, Hamborow</hi> and other places, to be ioyned with his Nauie. Or what effect wrought the consultation at <hi>Madrid,</hi> and the dayly posting with letters from thence to <hi>Bruxells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All came to iust nothing, quoth the D. of <hi>Sesa:</hi> for euen in the heate and threate of this great prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were so bold as to set vpon a goodly Ship of ours, whose lading was siluer, which they tooke and brought safely home to <hi>Horne:</hi> So that weighing all occurrences rightly, we shall finde it no time to thinke of an offensiue warre with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for which we are not in case, yet it is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse for vs to pretend like Lyons, and seeme terrible to the world, but necessity doth admonish, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing we must eeke and lengthen out our hides with Foxes tayle.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:176797:24"/>
            <p>Therefore in my opinion, it is best to make faire weather with <hi>England,</hi> in any case so long at the lest, till we haue tried the vttermost of our strength a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Holland,</hi> which I hope his Catholicke Maiesty our Maister will doe this Summer, and as I am infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, all those musters and taking vp of men which we heare are in <hi>Naples, Sicilie,</hi> the Dutchy of <hi>Millan, Spaine, Artois, Henalt, Luxemburge</hi> and other places, are to that end. For the doore being but halfe shut we had yet roome to enter, if we prolong the time we shall be so bard and bolted, that there will be no hope of entrance at all, except (quoth <hi>Don Lewes</hi> of <hi>Velasco</hi>) as my Lord Duke of <hi>Sesa</hi> saith in this <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitium</hi> or twi-light of Treatie, or suspence betweene Warre and Peace, we take to our selues some no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table aduantage, and followe opportunity close at the heeles, we are like howsoeuer we flatter our selues with gitting the game, to go away the greatest loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers: For we see whatsoeuer we entend the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> are still in action, dayly getting ground of vs. Did they not in <hi>August</hi> last recouer <hi>Mogodor</hi> in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia</hi> from vs? did not shortly after <hi>Graue Ernest</hi> take <hi>Embden</hi> (which <hi>Tillie</hi> supposed to be at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion) bringing in to the defence of the same 28. peeces of Count <hi>Mansfeilds</hi> great Ordinance? hath not the Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> with as great industry and care as <hi>Spinola</hi> on our parts (presently after the death of <hi>Obham</hi> the chiefe Admirall of <hi>Holland,</hi> who dyed this last yeare at the <hi>Hage</hi>) taken view of all the forts and Townes standing along the <hi>Mase Waell</hi> and the <hi>Rheine,</hi> put in stronger Garrisons into <hi>Rauenstein</hi> &amp; <hi>Genn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p,</hi> and after all this, made vp full the Armie of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:176797:25"/>
               <hi>Brunswick.</hi> Moreouer, hath he not strengthened and enabled to endure the longest siege <hi>Zutphen, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenter, Swoll,</hi> with the rest of the frontier Townes towards <hi>Frizeland,</hi> the passage we held euer to be our easiest and readiest for the subduing of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands? Did not those of the Garrison of <hi>Emme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> surprise and take <hi>Holden,</hi> a well fortified Towne hard by <hi>Dinxlaken,</hi> tooke all our <hi>Spaniards</hi> that lay there in garrison, and brought away the keyes of the Towne gate with them. On the other side, if we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing, it is either discouered (so vigilant are the States) ere it be acted, or faileth in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and meanes of the action. As that enterprise of ours vpon <hi>Isendike</hi> (notwithstanding we kept the gates of <hi>Antwerpe</hi> shut for two dayes together, and no man suffered to go out) which we intended vpon the sudden to surprise with our scaling-ladders, yet do what we could they had notice of our intent, that when we came before it we might (as they say) throw our caps at it, for euer winning or comming within it.</p>
            <p>And the like attempts (to no purpose) we made this last winter vpon <hi>Bortagna</hi> by <hi>Groening,</hi> and vpon St. <hi>Andres</hi> Scorne, had not the Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> thinke we, knowledge of Count <hi>Henry Vandem Berges</hi> iourney this last winter into <hi>Frizeland?</hi> yes doubtlesse, as the euent shewed. For he (vpon my knowledge) was secretly informed that the Spanish Horsemen had caused in <hi>Antwerpe</hi> and other places all their horse-shoes to be altered, and as many new to be made as would suffice for sixe or eight thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand norse all calked sharpe and frost-nayled of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:176797:25"/> for trauaile ouer the Ice, whereby hee knew (as hee is most circumspect and prouident) that some enterprise was to be attempted vpon either<note place="margin">The expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō of Count <hi>Henry Vanden-Berge,</hi> into <hi>Freezeland.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Holland</hi> or <hi>Frizeland:</hi> in that time of the great frost, all Fennes, Riuers, and Marishes, being passible by reason of the thicknes of the Ice (for it froze con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually) therefore he doubled the garrisons with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the frontier Towne, sent certaine troopes of horse, to obserue &amp; watch the most suspected pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for passage, and had shippes abroad to bring him tydinges vpon the least motion or occasion. Lastly, hee sent in waggons six thousand Skippers and Water-men to breake Ice in the most com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and likely places of passage, in the Riuers of <hi>Rhine, Isell,</hi> the <hi>Wael,</hi> and about the ditches of Townes, Marishes, and other places, neither did his Prognostication faile him. For Count <hi>Henry Vandenberg</hi> presently after our consultation at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drill,</hi> had his Commission at <hi>Brussels</hi> for eighteene thousand horse and foote: with which, and eleuen peeces of Ordinance, and a great multitude of Waggons, he passed by <hi>Emmerick,</hi> in exceeding bitter and cold weather towards <hi>Frizeland,</hi> but turning another way between <hi>Duisburgh</hi> &amp; <hi>Bronck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horst</hi> (a Castle belonging vnto the Graue of <hi>Stiru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> which he tooke and spoyled) he came to the <hi>Isell</hi> with 4. peeces of Ordinance, wherof one (the Ice breaking) sunke, the rest he left at <hi>Bronckhorst,</hi> hauing passed the Riuer, he fortified his foote at <hi>Diterbusch,</hi> with trees he filled vp the River. The Estates beleeuing hee went directly for <hi>Arnhem,</hi> they sent <hi>Marquet</hi> with troopes of horse and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:176797:26"/> foote Companies, but <hi>Vandenberge</hi> saluting the Towne with a volley of small shot, and beside, making a shot or two into the Towne with his great Ordinance departed, I heard great (quoth <hi>Pennatiore</hi>) outrages were by him committed in that Iourney, wherein he spared neither Age nor Sexe.</p>
            <p>Crueltie (replied <hi>Gonzales</hi>) is naturall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haerent to our Nation, for except our victories be drowned in blood, we cannot tast them. It is most true that he gaue way to his Souldiers in the depth and greatest bitternes of the frost and snow this last winter, to turne men and women starke naked out of their houses, to shift for themselues in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen fieldes, to rauish yong girles not aboue eight or ten yeares of age, wilfully to beate out the heads of their wine and beere vessells, that they might drinke only water in that extremitie of cold wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that many infants (their parents flying away for feare) at their returne, were found either starued for food, or frozen to death with the cold, hauing neither fire, nor clothing.</p>
            <p>What (quoth <hi>Don Pedro</hi>) slept the Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> all this while? or was no manner of reueng taken by the <hi>Dutch?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes, it seemed so (quoth <hi>Velasco,</hi>) for the most part of our Spanish souldiers were cut off, in their marching away and retreat, by the Garrisons of <hi>Duisburgh, Arnhem, Daventrie, Campen,</hi> and <hi>Zut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> beside great numbers who perished with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of cold, some hauing their noses, some their hands frozen and rotted off, beside those that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:176797:26"/> were starued for want of bread, so that wee cannot boast of this voyage, wee staying in the <hi>Velue</hi> but seuen dayes, which a Spaniard had not seene in aboue thirtie yeares before.</p>
            <p>All this discourse (quoth Count <hi>Gondomar</hi>) had on all sides, I see tendeth to no other end, then to intimate our disabilitie and disproportion of strength, if wee should vndertake a present warre against the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> without either making our selues Masters of great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> a thing which his Maiesties Predecessors for these hundred years haue aimed at (and we may truely say and beleeue is a matter impossible) or by faire meanes entreat them, from their cliffes of <hi>Dover,</hi> to bee but onely Spectators, while wee wrestle for the remnant of our right in the Low Countries, wherefore at the last, to end and shut vp this our Consultation, I haue (with Aduise) drawne together certaine Heads and Conclusions, as Maximes of State, for the present and future securing of our Countries and selues, which I humbly submit to all your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and honourable censures.</p>
            <p>Herewith <hi>Gondomar</hi> kissing the paper, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the same to the D: of <hi>Braganca,</hi> which the D. againe deliuered to a Secretarie of Estate, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him to reade them openly and distinctly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the whole house: the contents whereof were as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">1 First aboue all things to maintaine and vphold the Catholique Religion, against Pagans and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, and to doe our best to plant and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the same in all places of the world.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:176797:27"/>2 To hold fast, with both hands (if we can) the friendship of his Maiestie of great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> which setting and declining from vs, let vs labour to reassure and gaine by all meanes possible, vpon what pretence or condition soeuer, for hereupon depends the fortunate or ill successe of all our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, either now for the present or hereafter, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating herein good Enginers or workemen, when they would build a Bridge, to keepe off, or turne the maine Channell another way.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That being effected, otherwise let vs thinke neuer to take weapons in hand. Let (S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Gonzales) Spinola,</hi> with your selfe, breake at an instant into <hi>Brabant,</hi> and trie your strength vpon <hi>Breda,</hi> or <hi>Bergen op Zoom,</hi> giuing them an alarum in those parts, while Count <hi>Henry Vanden-Berge</hi> ioyned with <hi>Tillyes</hi> forces shall by <hi>Wezell</hi> or <hi>Rees,</hi> passing the <hi>Rhine,</hi> come like an inundation vpon them in <hi>Freezeland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 That our Garrisons be doubled in <hi>Dunkerk, Ostend,</hi> and other Townes of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens well guarded and defended.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That the Emperour take a truce for six yeares with his deadly Enemie <hi>Bethlem Gabor,</hi> and that we hold good correspondēce, with the D. of <hi>Savoy</hi> and the <hi>Venetians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 That all shipping be stayd, whether English, French, Scottish, Hamburgers, or of what Nation soeuer till our pleasure be further knowne.</p>
            <p n="7">7 That all our Magazines and store-houses be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and furnished, with all manner of Provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, lead, powder, match, bullets, and cordage.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:176797:27"/>8 That a certaine number of ships be newly built and sent into the West <hi>Indies,</hi> as well to secure and guard our Navy home, as to supplant those <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> who haue gotten footing in our Kingdome of <hi>Peru.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 That all strangers, of what Nation or Country soever, be banished the Land.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That we take an order for the reliefe of such Priests and Iesuites as shall be banished <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to increase the number of our Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencers.</p>
            <p n="11">11 That we barre the <hi>English, French, Dutch, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish,</hi> and other Nations whatsoever, from all accesse to the <hi>Indies,</hi> either to traffique or plant.</p>
            <p n="12">12 That we set vp and maintaine the Inquisition in all our Dominions, and to enhaunse our Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes.</p>
            <p n="13">13 That we make our selues able to encounter whosoever shall oppose, or stop our passage on the narrow Seas, and that we giue it out, (what ever our intent is) that our Fleets passe that way onely but for the chastising of the <hi>Hollander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14 That hereafter wee entertaine no <hi>English</hi> nor <hi>Scots</hi> into our pay, but the <hi>Irish</hi> onely, to the intent after they haue gotten experience, and are able to command, they may stand vs in stead, in case wee should hereafter make any attempt vpon <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 That we call in as much of our gold and silver as is possible.</p>
            <p n="16">16 That you speedily write to our Ambassadour in <hi>England,</hi> to giue notice to all our trustie well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved the <hi>Iesuites</hi> and secular <hi>Priests,</hi> with some of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:176797:28"/> the best minded <hi>Catholiques</hi> toward vs, that they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as much as in them lyeth to take away all as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persion, &amp; what soever may tend to our dishonor, &amp; for this cause to giue vs notice of all scandalous Bookes, Pictures, Invectiues, Pasquills, &amp;c. that shall be Printed against vs in <hi>Holland, England,</hi> and other places.</p>
            <p>That they curiously search into the proceedings of the Parliament, and send vs an abbreviate of all the passages thereof, with what forces, and how soone they resolue to succour the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, that in the Name of their obedience to his Holinesse, and observance to his Catholique Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, they labour where ever they liue, to educate and instruct their friends children in the Catholike Religion, and timely to enable either their sonnes for our Seminaries, or their daughters for our Nunneries, so the houses shall be supplied still with novices, our Treasuries with money, and we with friends and instruments at all occasions.</p>
            <p>Concerning these two last Propositions, for a conclusion I will produce a Letter vnto me subscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with the hande of many of the chiefe among them, (whose pourtraitures with their names yee haue here inserted) of the manner of their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and that you may know they spend not their time in vaine in <hi>England.</hi> For I must my LL: tell you I hold intelligence with the wisest and best learned among them, and where ever they are <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seo per medium illorum.</hi> Therefore I thought it not amisse by a draught to let you see them in their Consultation, as they were wont to sit at the house
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:176797:28"/> of one <hi>L.</hi> a Goldsmith in Fetter-lane by Holborne<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L:</hi> a Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smith; and one that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth the Printing of <hi>Popish</hi> books.</note> in <hi>London,</hi> this <hi>L.</hi> hath for many yeares closely kept a Printing house, to the great furtherance and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of the Catholique Religion in that Land, for by his meanes thousands &amp; thousands of good Books haue beene dispersed over the Land, which, albeit they are sold at an excessiue rate, and he hath beene a great gainer by them, yet are they printed and reprinted againe, and much money gotten by them though vttered at a third hand; but I will reade the Letter, it is not long: your Honors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore daigne it the hearing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Illustrious and excellent Lord▪</hi> it is now (wee all thinke) a long time since we heard from your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, or received any instruction from you concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the businesse you wot of, we in <hi>England</hi> here, are like shortly to groane vnder the heavie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>supportable burthen of persecution, but we shall (I hope) the better endure it, so long as our cause is warranted▪ and our constancy assisted and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the prayers &amp; supplications of the Church, we labour daily in the Catholique Harvest, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, (with wonderfull successe thousands of soules from the Abysse of Perdition into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some of the Church, the onely difficultie is in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing our selues and intendments, from that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny headded Monster Heresie. Wee walke openly and haue our time allotted vs till the 14 day of <hi>Iune</hi> next, which is the vtmost period of our stay, in the meane time we desire to be advised by your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, what afterward were fittest to be done of vs, for your Honors depth of iudgement and all-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:176797:29"/> pollicie, is the compasse by which we all Steere to escape present danger. Our Lord protect your Honor to all our Comforts; and our blessing be vpon you. From <hi>London</hi> this 3. of <hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>I haue here sett the true portrature of the Iesuits and prists: as they vse to sitt at Counsell in England to further y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Catholicke Cause.</hi>
               </p>
               <figDesc>depiction of priests</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <list>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:176797:29"/>
               <item>D. <hi>Wight.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>D. <hi>Bristow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Barlow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>D. <hi>Bishop.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Fisher.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Pattison.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Porter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>D. <hi>Smith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Sweete.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Ployden.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Louett.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Wothington.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Heyham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Palmer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>F. <hi>Townsend,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>To this Letter I gaue them this answer as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Holy Fathers,</hi> I received your Letters to my great comfort, but I confesse I am neerely touched with the so suddain approach of your common calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but as the greatest so are findeth his salue, so the greatest affliction some consolation or other in the middest of extremitie; For mine owne part know, that I will not be wanting to your comforts in any thing that in me lyeth, or that I can procure in your behalfes, either from his Holines at <hi>Rome,</hi> or my Master his Catholique Maiesty here. The times are dangerous, carry your selues therefore wisely with that perverse Nation, which scornes you, and hourely consulteth how to sweepe you from the face of the earth, and even now haue they the broome in their hands, I meane the present Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who will leaue no dust, or Sluts corners be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, favour you are to expect none there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, with the <hi>Foxe</hi> (when hunted out of breath) you must relie vpon your Arts, and subtle sleights. Of which nature may be these following. If your credits be so good with any great or eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonage, make him your Instrument to sow dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:176797:30"/> betwixt the Prince &amp; people, imitating herein souldiers, when they would get an advantage of flying or running away, they vse to set fire on villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and their baggage, that they might escape vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seene by the benefit of the smoake. Learne or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise new and the most difficult Characters for wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Letters, with all the slights and devises of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy conveyance; you may practise Physick as Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of <hi>Padua,</hi> or set vp bills as <hi>Mountebankes,</hi> ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting collor'd Oyles, Balsames, counterfeit Bezar, perfumd Lozenges, Receipts for the Tooth-ach, with a thousand the like: get the perfect and true receipt for any one disease or ach, it is enough to gaine credit to your practise, and make you passe for currant. If you send any youths over to our Seminaries, let them be the sonnes of the richest and ablest men, so shall you not want a place of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traict, and meanes to relieue you at an extremitie. Young Gentlewomen, you may convey over to <hi>Bruxells,</hi> or whither you please, by putting them in boyes apparell, their hayre being handsomely tyed vp with a Fillet, and a wrought cap worne over it with a great broad-brimmd Hat. If you would at any time convey over any Silver or Gold, the Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher commonly may be couzoned, if you send it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in Pasties baked, provided that you haue some of flesh onely to eate or giue away, as a cullor for the rest. For the venting of hallowed Oyle, Beades, <hi>Agnus-Deies,</hi> Maddalles, Pardons, Crucifixes, &amp;c. You may doe it by some one poore yet trustie Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique or two, to goe vp and downe the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie in the habit and nature of Pedlers: this also is a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:176797:30"/> good way to hold intelligence with friends in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places. I haue knowne some vnder the cullour of selling <hi>Tobacco,</hi> haue carried Letters handsomly, privily in the balls or roules▪</p>
            <p>Also we advise you, if persecutions come vpon you, to fly into <hi>Scotland</hi> for a season, and when you see your best time returne againe; for it seemeth by this Proclamation you sent, that you are not bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed <hi>Scotland,</hi> therefore that may be a good shelter vnto you.</p>
            <p>Be sure to haue going in the <hi>North</hi> or <hi>West</hi> part of <hi>England,</hi> two Printers Presses at worke, which let be well stocked; also a small rouling presse for little Pictures of Saints, <hi>Veronica's</hi> heads, Crucifixes, and the like, much money may be gained hereby.</p>
            <p>Haue a care whensoever any Booke or Picture comes out to our preiudice, set some friends to buy them all vp, though you burne them forthwith, except some few, which faile not still but to send vs of every sort three at the least, for they will be vnto vs of great vse.</p>
            <p>Many moe directions (Holy Fathers) there are which are alike necessary to be thought vpon, but I referre them to your owne graue and pious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations. So committing you to the tuition of our blessed Lady, and my selfe to your holy and devout Prayers, I rest. From <hi>Sevill</hi> this 6. of <hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Count <hi>Gondomar</hi> having made an end, they all with one voyce applauded and highly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his directions and counsell, not onely for his particular Letter, but for the wise carriage of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:176797:31"/> heretofore in many and weightie affayres that concerned the Catholique Religion, the honor of his Maiestie, and the generall good of the Estate. Esteeming him worthily honored with the title of a <hi>Grande</hi> at home in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and of his Masters Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadour abroad, having effected more by his wit and policy, then could haue beene wrought by the strength of many Armies.</p>
            <p>And now when they were come almost to a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, and full conclusion of their Consultation for that time, there came a Messenger in post, who brought letters from the King to Count <hi>Olivares</hi> his favorite, to call him to the Court vpon some speciall imployment, what it was, could not bee certainely knowne, but as I heard, some complaint was lately come out of England, against the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadors resident there; &amp; moreouer that a great fight had beene lately betweene nine great Spanish ships, &amp; 5. men (or ships) of warre of <hi>Horne</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chuisen</hi> in Holland, wherein, the report went, the Hollanders had taken two, and sunke one, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, they all arose vp together in a great confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, euery one hasting to his horse which stood rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in a faire base Court without, they tooke their way, some with <hi>Olivares</hi> to the Court, others to their places of charge and command, the rest to their owne houses, where I leaue them, till wee heare further of their proceedings.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:176797:31"/>
            <head>TO THE ILLVSTRIOVS, <hi>MAGNIFIQVE, AND GRAVE</hi> Assembly of the High Court of <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HEere as in a little glasse, may you (Most Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, Great, and Graue <hi>Senate</hi>) viewe the <hi>Epitome,</hi> or rather effect of a seuen yeares Treatie with Spaine, yee may plainely see the hold and assurance we were euer like to haue had of that Nation, yea, euen when we thought our selues surest of them. Here we may (to our warning of taking heede whom we trust) behold to the life the Hauty-Pride, Thirsty-Couetousnes, and kind dissimulation of that same Fox <hi>Populi,</hi> Count <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domar,</hi> the <note n="*" place="margin">For they say, he is a <hi>Grandè</hi> in <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </note> Great. Heere may the <hi>Netherlands</hi> perceiue the imminent danger that hung ouer their heads, shortly without doubt to haue fallen vpon them, had not the Spanish ambushes beene timously discouered. Heere may that Illustrious King, and the most renowned and second Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (for her constancy and spirit) of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> and Princes <hi>Palatines</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> consider how assuredly faithfully the surrendring of their <hi>Palatinate</hi> should haue beene performed. In a word, heere may wee all see the great mercies of <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>